Guide to the AIDS/Brooklyn Exhibition collection 1993.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
AIDS/Brooklyn Exhibition collection
1987-1997
1992-1993
Brooklyn Historical Society
1993.001
11.88 Linear Feet in 10 manuscript boxes, 3 small flat boxes, 2 oversize flat boxes, and 5 flat file folders.
46.79 Gigabytes in 133 files, total running time: 34 hours, 2 minutes, 59 seconds.
This collection includes oral histories and print materials collected and donated for the AIDS/Brooklyn exhibition, undertaken by the Brooklyn Historical Society in the early 1990s. The project was developed to document the impact of the AIDS epidemic on Brooklyn communities.
The digitized portions of this collection are available on our oral history portal.
Historical Note
Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS) began preparing the exhibition AIDS/Brooklyn in 1991. David M. Kahn, Executive Director of BHS at the time, had lost his partner, Ron Wogaman, to an AIDS-related illness earlier that year. The exhibition, which opened in 1993, aimed to document the crisis in Brooklyn through the material culture, personal narratives, and life histories of those living with HIV/AIDS. This exhibition was a part of BHS's institution-wide efforts to be more responsive to contemporary events in Brooklyn through exhibits, collection development, and education.
Robert Rosenberg, a documentary film producer, was hired as project director. Robert Sember, a New York University doctoral candidate in Performance Studies, also conducted many of the interviews. Kathryn Pope, a research assistant, made initial contacts with people and organizations affected by HIV/AIDS or involved in advocacy. The Brooklyn Historical Society's Museum Division staff also worked on this exhibition: Ellen Snyder-Grenier (Chief Curator at the start of the project), Daniel Barron (Curator of Collections), and Dwandalyn Reece (Chief Curator starting in November 1992).
Community Advisory and Scholarly Advisory Committees provided guidance throughout the process. The Community Advisory Committee was involved with identifying individuals and organizations in Brooklyn to reach out to for interviews and donations of materials. The exhibition team printed flyers in English, Spanish, and Haitian Creole and sent them to community and healthcare organizations related to HIV/AIDS issues. This outreach effort was also publicized in the press.
At the time of the exhibition in 1993, the borough of Brooklyn had an estimated 35,000 cases of HIV. There, as in the rest of the nation, the disease was disproportionately affecting African American, Latino, and gay communities. Brooklyn, however, was experiencing demographic shifts in the spread of AIDS that differed from the considerable high-impact zone of Manhattan. The disease was impacting women and children in Kings County; over 1800 women had HIV/AIDS in 1992, according to the city's AIDS Surveillance Unit. Nationwide, estimated deaths from AIDS peaked in 1995; over 50,000 U.S. residents died that year. Due primarily to multi-drug treatment and lowering infection rates, the number has since declined.
Historical note bibliography:
Tabor, Mary B.W. "Chronicling the Spread of AIDS Throughout Brooklyn." New York Times (New York, NY), May 31, 1992.
Wong, Sumi. "Historical Society at Work On Show About a Very Contemporary Subject: the AIDS Epidemic and Its Impact on Brooklyn Residents." The Phoenix (Brooklyn, NY), September 25, 1992.
Young, Joyce. "Exhibit takes closer look at life with AIDS." New York Daily News (New York, NY), April 18, 1993.
Scope and Contents
The AIDS/Brooklyn Exhibition collection includes oral histories conducted and materials collected for an exhibition undertaken by the Brooklyn Historical Society in 1993.
The oral history recordings, initially made on magnetic tape, were with narrators who had firsthand experience with the crisis in their communities, families, and personal life. Narrators came from Brooklyn and the New York metropolitan area and had different experiences that connected them with HIV/AIDS. Topics that come up in the oral histories include: hemophilia, sexual behavior, addiction, medical practice, social work, homelessness, activism, childhood, relationships, and parenting.
The print and audiovisual materials collected by BHS staff or donated to BHS for the exhibition include flyers, brochures, posters, HIV/AIDS medication and treatment information, obituaries, photographs, VHS tapes, and an audiocassette tape. Donated materials represent the work of HIV/AIDS awareness and advocacy organizations and individuals' lives.
Arrangement
The AIDS/Brooklyn Exhibition collection is organized into three series:
Series 1: Oral histories, 1992-1993
Series 2: Collected materials, 1985-1994
Series 3: Donated materials, 1945-1997
Conditions Governing Access
The oral histories are open to researchers with varied restrictions according to narrator agreement. Oral histories can be accessed on site at the Center for Brooklyn History's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal.
The other materials are open to users without restriction onsite at the Othmer Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The oral histories that make up this collection were compiled by a team including a project director, researcher and a research assistant. Staff for this project included Dwandalyn Reece King (Chief Curator), Robert Rosenberg (Project Director and Interviewer), Robert Sember (Researcher and Interviewer), and Kathryn Pope (Research Assistant).
These materials were gathered by Brooklyn Historical Society's Museum Division and transferred to the Library collections in 1997.
Related Archival Materials
The Center for Brooklyn History holds the following related collections:
The Crown Heights History Project oral histories (1994.006) includes a 1993 interview with Dellon Wilson, a volunteer in the AIDS community.
Brooklyn photograph and illustration collection (ARC.202) has exhibition photographs, also digitized and available on the digital collections.
Brooklyn Historical Society Institutional Archives (ARC.288)
Related collections located elsewhere include:
The AIDS Activist Videotape Collection, 1985-2000 at the New York Public Library (MssCol 3622) includes an interview with Iris De La Cruz and a series of oral histories conducted by Gay Men's Health Crisis.
The ACT UP Oral History Project videotapes, 2002-2008, at the New York Public Library (MssCol 6148)
AIDS correspondence (TRACER) archives, 1982-1990, at the National Library of Medicine, History of Medicine Division (MS C 607)
Separated Materials
Objects collected for this exhibition were separated into Center for Brooklyn History's Art and Artifacts collection and individually cataloged. These objects are currently separate, but are to be intellectually arranged with this collection.
AIDS activists -- United States; AIDS (Disease) -- New York (State) -- New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- History -- 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; HIV infections |z New York (State) |z New York; HIV-positive persons |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interviews (sound recordings); Oral histories (document genres); Self-help groups |z New York (State) |z New York; Sexual health |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social group work |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Stigma (Social psychology) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transcripts; Political posters; Public health posters; Brochures; Flyers (printed matter); Medical care |z New York (State) |z Kings County; AIDS (Disease) -- Patients -- Services for -- New York (State) -- New York; Blood coagulation factors; Hemophiliacs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hemophilia |z United States; Immunological deficiency syndromes; Marriage customs and rites |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gay culture |z New York (State) |z New York; Gays |x Social life and customs; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Paratransit services |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Prostitution |z New York (State) |z New York; Safe sex in AIDS prevention |z New York (State); Women |x Social conditions |x Poetry; Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); AZT (Drug); Fashion designers |z New York (State) |z New York; Hepatitis B; Women's health services -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Caribbean Americans; Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Drug addiction |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Methadone maintenance |z New York (State) |z New York; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Nurses |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Voluntarism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Boerum Hill (New York, N.Y.); Funeral rites and ceremonies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Medicaid; Physicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; ACT UP New York (Organization); Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc; Haitian Coalition on AIDS; Green-Wood Cemetery (New York, N.Y.); White, Ryan, Ryan; Kings County Hospital (Kings County, N.Y.); United States. Department of State; De La Cruz family; Cuomo, Mario Matthew; NYU Langone Medical Center; People with AIDS Coalition of New York; Housing Works, Inc.; Wyckoff Heights Medical Center (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Women's Health Association; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (U.S.); Hispanic AIDS Forum; Lutheran Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Maimonides Hospital of Brooklyn; Riker's Island (N.Y.)
- Series 1: Oral histories, 1992-1993
  Existence and Location of Copies
  The transcripts and most of the interviews are available online on the Oral History Portal.
  Arrangement
  The series is in the order imposed by the initial processing archivist.
  Oral History Note
  Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Center for Brooklyn History archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
  1. The Center for Brooklyn History abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
  2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, CBH presents these views as recorded.
  3. Transcripts created prior to 2008 serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because CBH gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
  4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes oral history interviews on original and duplicate audio cassettes, along with transcripts of the interviews with Barbara Norris, Mildred Pearson, Kenny Post and Cheryl Wagner, Dolores Rivera, Luis E. Nieves Rosa, and William Sandoval with Rita Rodriguez. Summaries of all of the interviews written by the project coordinators and photographs of some of the interviewees are also included.
  Some of the interviewees also donated materials for the exhibition. These materials are described in Series 3: Donated Materials, 1945-1996, of this finding aid.
  - Broman, Melinda, 1992 June 20; 1993.001.01 (Box 11, Cassette 1, Cassette 2, Box 12)
    Biographical / Historical
    Melinda Broman, a white woman, was 47 years old when she was interviewed. Her husband Victor Ockey, who had hemophilia, died of acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS) in 1989. He was infected with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) during a routine blood transfusion in the early 1980s. At the time of this interview, Broman had lived in Brooklyn's Cobble Hill neighborhood since the mid-1980s. Broman's involvement with AIDS was extensive, reaching beyond her relationship with her husband. As a member of the National Hemophilia Foundation she has lobbied for increased awareness of the specific plight of HIV+ hemophiliacs. Through her work as a psychologist at Downstate Medical Center and as a member of the Brooklyn Psychological Association she has organized AIDS workshops. She was interviewed primarily because of her personal and professional experience with AIDS issues specific to people with hemophilia.
    In the interview, Melinda Broman provides information about her experience as a heterosexual woman within a straight relationship dealing with HIV/AIDS. She speaks about the lack of support within the AIDS movement and also the lack of support from the hemophiliac community. Broman made friends with gay men active in the AIDS movement, but did not always feel she was getting the support she needed. It was different within the community of people with hemophilia. She felt that fear of HIV/AIDS made the virus an unwanted topic of discussion. Melinda Broman also speaks about being in a serodiscordant couple and how it related to handling her own non-HIV-related health issues. Interview conducted by Robert Sember.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Original and duplicate cassette tapes are not available for research use. Access to the interview is available digitally onsite at Center for Brooklyn History's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal.
    Two original audio cassettes. Two duplicate audio cassettes.
    Three preservation .WAV files. One access .mp3 file.
  - Coleman, Philip, 1992 June 13; 1993.001.02 (Box 11, Cassette 3, Cassette 4, Box 12)
    Philip Coleman was 52 years old at the time of the interview in 1992. A gay African American person with AIDS (PWA), he was born in Harlem, New York, lived on the Upper West Side of Manhattan for many years, and was living alone in the East Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn during the time of this interview. Coleman was a member of Gay Men's Health Crisis (GMHC) and he conducted sensitivity training for volunteers working with gay African Americans before he was diagnosed. In 1992, he participated in a HIV positive support group for gay men in Brooklyn. He had been ill for some time and had previously been hospitalized with respiratory and circulation ailments shortly before this interview.
    In the interview, Philip Coleman talks about the impact that AIDS has had on the Black gay community and on his life. He speaks about what love, sex and relationships have come to mean to him as a PWA. He makes some observations about gay PWAs living in Brooklyn, based on the experiences he had in his support group. Coleman shares his thoughts and feelings rooted in the intersectional experience of being Black, gay, and living with HIV throughout the interview. He talks about what he thinks was needed in terms of activism and services, and how racism and homophobia play out in church, in community, and elsewhere. Throughout the interview, Coleman connects the work he does around his being a gay Black man living with HIV to issues such as ageism, the house music and ballroom dance scenes, and even overlapping activism as it related to Haiti. Interview conducted by Robert Sember.
  - Rotter, Beverly and family of Iris De La Cruz, 1992 April 03; 1993.001.03 (Box 11, Cassette 5, Box 12)
    Iris De La Cruz is the daughter of narrator Beverly Rotter, mother to Melissa De La Cruz and sister to Randy Rotter. Beverly was one of the founders of Iris House, a care facility for women living with HIV, where she was also on the board of directors. She also founded Mothers March Against AIDS. At the time of this 1992 interview, Melissa was working with Lifeforce, doing safer sex education. Randy was self-employed during this period. Beverly Rotter died in October 2015.
    Beverly Rotter, Melissa De La Cruz, and Randy Rotter are interviewed as a family group. They discuss Iris De La Cruz (1954 - 1991) and the powerful mark she made on the world as an AIDS activist, sex worker activist, and writer. They talk about her life and work before HIV and after. Each one remarks on Iris's humor, kindness, and fierceness as an activist. Melissa talks about what it was like to have Iris as her mother. Randy discusses bonding with Iris through humor, and also his anger around her HIV infection. Beverly speaks about being a caregiver and the work that it takes to advocate for someone. Each also speaks about their own understanding of HIV/AIDS before Iris seroconverted (when HIV antibodies are detected) and after. Criticizing stigma and discrimination of people with HIV/AIDS, Beverly Rotter tells the interviewer that their line of questioning is inappropriate and lets him know she will not continue in that direction. Interview conducted by Robert Rosenberg.
    Original and duplicate cassette tapes are not available for research use. Access to the interview is only available onsite at Center for Brooklyn History's Othmer Library.
    One original audio cassette. One duplicate audio cassette.
    Two preservation .WAV files. One access .mp3 file.
  - Fernandes, Carney and Kristy, 1993 January 11; 1993.001.04 (Box 11, Cassette 6, Box 12)
    At the time of this 1993 interview, Kristy Fernandes was a seven year old girl who had been diagnosed with AIDS two years prior. Kristy's father, Carney Fernandes, was 55 years old at the time of the interview. Carney Fernandes was an immigrant from Guyana and had tested negative for HIV. He had been caring for his daughter on his own since her mother's death in the late 1980s. Upon learning of his daughter's HIV status he went back to school to become a nurse. Kristy was aware of her diagnosis and able to keep up with her school work and had only minor limitations on her daily life. They lived together in an apartment in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    In the interview, the narrators discuss Kristy Fernandes' HIV positive status and Carney Fernandes' role as primary caregiver. Kristy talks about her friends, the care she has received, what she wants to be when she grows up, and disclosure at school. Carney talks about Kristy's mother, his previous relationships, and how he has dealt with Kristy's health. Based on his experiences, he presents his ideas of what work has to be done to better respond to HIV/AIDS. Carney is vocal about AIDS issues and the community. He provides insight as a straight man of color not living with HIV who is profoundly impacted by the virus. Interview conducted by Robert Rosenberg.
  - Hargrove, Jason, 1992 February 4; 1993.001.05 (Box 11, Cassette 7, Box 12)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access to this recording is restricted by the donor. Please contact digitalcollections@bklynlibrary.org for further questions.
    Original and duplicate cassette tapes are not available for research use.
  - Henry, Christopher, 1992 October 2; 1993.001.06 (Box 11, Cassette 8, Cassette 9, Box 12)
    Christopher Henry, a gay African American man, tested positive for HIV four years before this interview. This was discovered a few weeks before his cousin, who was also gay, died from AIDS. He moved from his family home in the Bronx into his cousin's house in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1991. Apart from attending support groups at Woodhull Hospital, Henry was not involved with AIDS-related organizations or activities at the time of the interview. Henry did not consider himself an activist because he did not carry banners. Instead, Henry saw himself more as a public intellectual in the making, akin to a celebrity or "public official." He was close to family, had a sense of community, and was raised with a Christian foundation.
    In the interview, Christopher Henry speaks of AIDS from the position of a young gay man of color living in a city. He is conscious of the role race and ethnicity play in understanding the issues raised by the AIDS crisis. He describes his mother's reaction to his HIV positive status and interactions with gay friends. Henry provides insights into the views of people impacted by HIV in Brooklyn related to the systemic issues of HIV/AIDS. He speaks about HIV being created by the government as well as how the government's inaction impacts care. He talks about the ignorance he sees within his own Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. He discusses the virus in the contexts of spirituality, gay rights, and race. Interview conducted by Robert Sember.
    Two original audio cassettes. One duplicate audio cassette.
  - John, Marilyn, 1992 June 23; 1993.001.07 (Box 11, Cassette 10, Box 12, Cassette 9)
    Marilyn John, a Trinidadian woman, was thirty-four years old at the time of the interview in 1992. A graduate of Long Island University, she was once program coordinator for one of the AIDS programs at the Caribbean Women's Health Association (CWHA) in the Flatbush section of Brooklyn. She also had a private AIDS consulting business and represented Caribbean AIDS concerns at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. John saw the impact AIDS had on Brooklyn's Caribbean communities, as well as the experience of AIDS service providers. In the years following this interview, John became executive director of the CWHA and an employee of the New York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene. In 2010, John pled guilty in federal court to embezzlement and fraud charges. In 2016, she was the National Ambassadors Coordinator for the faith-based White House Prayer for Our Nation initiative.
    In the interview, Marilyn John speaks about the changes she has witnessed within Caribbean communities, particularly with regards to sexuality, because of the AIDS crisis. John brings to the conversation her experience from within the Caribbean community, as well as a background and interest in community health. Throughout the course of the interview, John talks about the need for a holistic approach to health (Holistic Methods of Intervention), specifically with a focus on culture and immigration. She also talks about the need for Caribbean-specific cultural training related to HIV. Since her primary interest is in education, she concentrates on the approaches she takes to address different needs and characteristics of the communities she works with. Finally, she outlines what should be done for Brooklyn's Caribbean communities. Interview conducted by Robert Sember.
  - Morciglio, Adolph, 1992 June 1; 1993.001.08 (Box 11, Cassette 11, Box 12, Cassette 10)